Guide to the H.K. Porter Co., Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1877-1968 AIS.1973.15
ULS Archives Service Center
H.K. Porter Co., Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1877-1968
AIS.1973.15
ULS Archives Service Center
1.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains the records of H.K. Porter Co. for the years 1877-1968. H.K. Porter was a major manufacturer of light locomotives from 1867-1941. Today, H.K. Porter is known for industrial products such as rubber belts, valves, and springs.
H. K. Porter Company.
History
H.K. Porter Co. began in 1866 with the name Smith Porter. In 1871 the company's name changed to Porter, Bell Co and then to H. K. Porter Co. in 1878. H.K. Porter was the leading manufacturer of light locomotives in the United States from 1867-1941, and the leading locomotive builder in Pittsburgh for 83 years.
In the United States large industrial locomotives dominated the national market while light locomotives dominated the exported. During the period 1900-1930, H.K. Porter specialized in export equipment ranging from light, functional cars to portable track. Several of the smaller locomotive builders, like The Gregg Company Ltd., furnished the engines for H.K. Porter which were shipped overseas.
Although it originally offered no product but the light locomotive, H.K. Porter diversified after 1900. The industrial products for which H.K. Porter is known today, rubber belts, hoses, high voltage electrical equipment, springs, and valves finally overshadowed the declining locomotive business. Porter ceased locomotive production in 1950 and sold its entire business to Davenport-Besler Corporation of Davenport, Iowa. Davenport later conveyed its locomotive interests to a Canadian Locomotive Company. H.K. Porter Co. functions today as an industrial supply manufacturer operating as H.K. Porter.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the records of H.K. Porter Company for the years 1877-1968. The collection consists of seven folders of paper records and four folders of photographs. Included are photographs, locomotive cards, reports, and a production list. Of particular interest is a report of locomotives damaged in Pittsburgh during the Great Railroad Strike of July 1877.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were a gift of Mrs. Lester C. Hill, June 1973.
Previous Citation
H.K. Porter Co., 1877-1968, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
H. K. Porter Company.; Business and Industry; Industries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Locomotive industry -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Locomotives -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Maintenance and repair; Transportation
- List of Locomotives (#155-#2559) built by H.K Porter Co., 1873-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Estimated Cost of Repairs to Locomotives of Pennsylvania Railroad and Pittsburgh, Cincinnati and St. Louis Railroad Burned During Riot -- July, 1877 (Folder 2)
- Willis E. Martin, Treasurer-- Mourning Card, January 12, 1920 (Folder 3)
- Stockholder form letters, December 9, 1925 (Folder 4)
- Pittsburgh Dispatch, "After a New Charter,", March 16, 1899 (Folder 5)
- The Bulletin Index, "H. K. Porter Co. Locomotives Chug around the World but their day is on the Wane.", April 30, 1936 (Folder 6)
- Annual Reports (4), 1965-1968 (Folder 7)
- Photographs, c1880-1920
  - Portaits of Henry Kirke Porter, c1880-1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Company officers (group shot at a formal dinner), c1900; 1. (Folder 2)
  - Logging Locomotive built by Porter, Bell & Co. for the Lake George and Mukegon River Railroad (Farwell, Michigan), 1890 (Folder 3)
  - Locomotive Advertising Cards (13), 1900 (Folder 4)